Guide to the Washington State University Womens Physical Education Department Records 1923-1976
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Washington State University Womens Physical Education Department Records
1923-1976
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 19
Washington State University. Women's Physical Education Department.
1 Linear feet of shelf space 2 Boxes
Collection contains correspondence, financial reports, preparatory notes for productions, programs, photographs, etc. There are also scrapbooks and programs related to the annual activities day.
Women's physical education at WSU began in 1901-02. Nine years later folk dancing was introduced into the program. Since that time dance has become an increasingly significant part of the women's physical education curriculum.
For further history, see "The History of the Development of the Women's Physical Education Major Program of the State College of Washington, From its Inception in 1919, to 1929," by Maxine Hazel Smith, Pullman, 1951 (Unpublished M.A. thesis).
The records of the Women's Physical Education Department span the years 1923 through 1976 and are concerned with dance, gymnastics, and the Physical Education Majors (P.E.M.) Club. The collection includes correspondence news, program preparations and schedules, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
The papers are grouped in two series. The first series contains correspondence (1923-1927) between W.S.U. faculty and Miss Elizabeth Burchenal, a folk dance specialist who conducted institutes on campus. Also in the first series are materials from the annual dance/gymnastics festival as well as other dance related activities. Memorabilia from the annual P.E.M. Club high school activities day, the club charter, and the club constitution make up the second series.
The papers are grouped in two series: Series 1. Dance, Series 2. Physical Education Majors Club. Within the series, the original order is maintained.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The Women's Physical Education Department records were donated to the Washington State University Library by Professor Jane Harris Ericson in June 1977. (UA 77-15)
Washington State University Womens Physical Education Department Records, 1973-1981 (Archives 300)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University. Women's Physical Education Department -- Records and correspondence.; State College of Washington. Women's Physical Education Department -- Records and correspondence.; State College of Washington. Women's Physical Education Department.
Physical education for women -- Washington (State) -- Pullman; Women athletes -- Washington (State)
Sports and Recreation; Colleges and Universities; Women; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Dance
  - Correspondence 1923-27 (Burchenal), 73 items (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1949; 27 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Reports, 1926-1935; 45 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Programs and Publicity, 1926-1944; 7 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Square Dance, 1951-1954; 25 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dance Festival, 1959-1970; 313 items (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
- Series 2: Physical Education Majors Club
  - Annual Activities Day
    - 1961-1968, 17 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1965, 17 items (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1968, 11 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1969, 20 items (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1970, 27 items (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1971, 27 items (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1972, 26 items (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1973, 18 items (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1974, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1975, 18 items (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1976, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - P.E.M. Club Constitution and Charter, 1963-1968; 10 items (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - P.E.M. Club Scrapbook, 1969-1975 (Box Oversize)